Luis Velez

CTO/Engineer

Contact

Address: Tampa, FL, 34695

Github: github.com/luis-israel-velez

E-mail: <u>luis.israel.velez@gmail.com</u>

Tech Skills

Languages: Scala, C#, Python, C++, Shell (Scripting), SQL, JS & TypeScript, HTML & CSS

Data Storage & Processing: Spark,
ALDS/GCS/S3, Databricks,
Snowflake, RDBMS, ELK Stack,
Netezza, Mongo, Kafka/Confluent

Cloud Ecosystem: Azure/GCP/AWS

Library & Frameworks: Node JS, React, Kubernetes, Hortonwork

Devops: Terraform (IaC), Azure Devops, Github, Helm, Docker.

Soft Skills

Leadership: Successfully built and expanded teams always building a strong connection with the individuals and their commitment to the mission.

Agile: Extensive experience building & leading teams.

Communication: Able to communicate clearly at different technical levels.



Work History

2021-08 - Chief Technology Officer

Current Company: Customer X.i

Company: Customer X.i Region: Dallas, TX

- · Hired & trained **technology team (25+)** from multiple disciplines (**Architecture/Software/Devops/Quality/Data & UI/UX**) both on-shore and off-shore. Worked with multiple companies to achieve best price and talent.
- · Built multiple enterprise-level web applications on Azure Cloud Infrastructure & Kubernetes. These applications allowed users to self-onboard their Point-of-Sales data using pre-built connectors to obtain near real time insights in the form of multiple dashboards.
- · Deployed a supporting data platform eco-system composed of a delta lake on ADLS Gen 2 (capable of storing TB of data in multiple cleaning stages), data pipelines using Databrick (capable of processing and calculating value for our customers) and a orchestration layer.
- · Established **engineering practices/protocols** to ensure quick and efficient development. This included **Agile and CI/CD** on all our repositories as well as code standards, checklists and SQA Automatic Testing. This also include **Infrastructure as Code** to maximize speed of delivery for new features.
- · Managed application/cloud & teams cost working with other executives, built KPI and Executive Dashboards to track efforts across the teams.
- · Worked directly with customers, consulting companies and 3rd party application platforms to **increase CX.i relationship** and **achieve our business aoals**.

2015-01 - Director of Data Engineering

2021-07 **Company**: Catalina Marketing

Progression: Lead-Manager-Director

· Lead **Data Engineering teams (50+)** from multiple disciplines (Architecture/ETL/DBA/Data/Quality/Devops). The teams included **multiple** worldwide offices and stakeholders.

Region: Tampa, FL

- **Built/Managed over (25+) data solutions** for different worldwide stakeholders. These solutions were used by multiple CPG/Retailers and agencies.
- · Responsible for **Data Platform dealing with over 300 TB, millions of transactions per day** and spanning different **Legacy and Cloud technology**.
- · Executed company **Legacy to Cloud migration** strategy, achieving success in executing our existing suite of tools successfully.
- \cdot Custodian of the technology budget allocated for data management. This included **multi-million-dollar contracts around technology** licensing,

Social Impact

NGT 360: High School Tech Mentoring Program.

Tech Mentoring: Instructor in multiple training programs.

Softtek Solidaria: Was the president of the community outreach program.

resource management and support infrastructure.

2011-06 - ETL Informatica Consultant

2014-12 **Company**: Sofftek PR

 \cdot Responsible for maintenance and support of the **Datawarehouse for one of the largest Health Care Company** in Puerto Rico.

Region: Guaynabo, PR

- · Designed and **developed an orchestration application** that was adopted **company wide** and used in all our customers projects. The application used linux-scripts, XML based contracts, RDBM's system to store audit information and Informatica for execution.
- Lead multiple projects for different customers as either a Solutions Architect or in charge of training junior personal.
- · Worked directly with multiple customers in the **Telecommunication/Banking** and **Health industry**. Gathered requirements, analyzed business needs and came up with data solutions that fit their challenges.
- · Analyze business needs to generate data solutions that fit those specific challenges. Solutions were built with Informatica and multiple RDBMs.

2010-05 - Software Engineer

2010-09

Company: Hamilton Sundstrand **Region:** Hartford, CT

Progression: Intern (Summer 2008 and 2009) – Software Engineer

- · Built features for **ORION GUI**
- · Tested fault-detection classes using emulators
- · Worked with Data Structure/Classes to provide more info on testing



Education

Master of Science: IT Management & Security Assurance

Polytechnic University - Guaynabo, PR

Bachelor of Science: Computer Science

University of Puerto Rico - Bayamon - Bayamon, PR